[[jsf">
== JavaServer Faces - JSF
[[jsf_overview">
=== What is JSF
		
			JavaServer Faces (JSF) is a UI component based Java Web
			application
			framework. JSF is serverbased, e.g. the JSF UI components
			and their
			state
			are represented on the server with a defined life cycle
			of
			the UI components. JSF  is part of
			the Java EE standard.
			
		
			A JSF application run in a
			standard web
			container, for example
http://www.vogella.com/tutorials/ApacheTomcat/article.html[Tomcat]
			or
http://www.vogella.com/tutorials/Jetty/article.html[Jetty]
			.
		
		
			This articles provides an introduction to JSF using only standard JSF
			features.
			For the usage of special Apache Trinidad features please see
http://www.vogella.com/tutorials/ApacheMyFaces/article.html[Apache Myfaces Trinidad with Eclipse - Tutorial]
			.
		

[[jsf_application">
=== A JSF application
		 A JSF application consists of web pages with JSF UI components.
			A JSF application requires also some configuration files
			("faces-config.xml" and
			`web.xml`). 
		
			The faces-config.xml defines:

			
				* Managed Bean - the data elements of the JSF
						application
						(managed beans and
						backing
						beans) Represents a Java class which will
						be created dynamically
						during runtime of the JSF application. It
						can be defined for which
						scope the bean is valid (Session, Request,
						Application or none).

						  
				
				* the navigation
						between
						web pages    
				
				* data validators - Used to check the validity of UI input
					
				
				* data converters -Used to translate between UI and model
					
				
			
		
		
			Managed beans are
			simple Java objects (POJO's) which are
			declared
			in
			"faces-config.xml"
			and can be used in an JSF application.
			For example
			you can define a
			Java object "Person". Once you define the
			object in
			faces-config.xml
			you can use the attributes of Person in your
			JSF UI
			components, e.g.
			by binding the value "firstName" of this object
			to an
			JSF input
			field.
		
		 JSF uses the Unified Expression Language (EL) to bind UI
			components to object attributes or methods. 

[[jsf_valuebinding">
=== Value and Method Binding
		 In JSF you can access the values of a managed bean via
			value
			binding. For value binding the universal Expression
			Language (EL) is
			used (to access bean and / or methods). In JSF you
			do not need to
			specify the get() or set() method but just the
			variable name.
		 Method binding can be used to bind a JSF component, e.g. a
			button to an method of a Java class.
		
			TIP:  Expression Language statements either start with "${" or with
				"#{"
				and end with "}". JSP EL expressions are using the ${...}
				syntax.
				These EL expressions are immediately evaluated. JSF EL
				expressions
				are of the type #{...}. These are only evaluated when
				needed (and
				otherwise stored as strings).
		

[[jsf_prerequisites">
=== Prerequisites to use JSF
		
			To use JSF you need:
			
				* 
					JSF Implementation (in the form of the JSF jars)
				
				* 
					The JSTL tags library
				
				* 
					A Java runtime environment
				
				* 
					A web-container to use JSF in (for example Tomcat)
				

			
		



[[jsf_mainfeatures">
=== JSF Main features
		
			JSP has the following main features:
			
				* 
					JSP is based on the Model-View-Controller concept
				
				* 
					JSP has a stateful UI component model, e.g. each component is
						aware of its data
				
				* 
					JSF separates the functionality of a component from the
						display of the component. The renderer is responsible of
						displaying the component for a certain client. This renderer can
						get
						exchanged. The
						standard
						renderer for JSF components is the HTML
						renderer.
				
				* 
					JSP support listeners on UI components
				
				* 
					JSP support data validation, data binding and data conversion
						between the UI and the model
				
			
		

[[jsf_jsp">
=== JSP and JSF
		 In this tutorial the JSF application will be build based on
			JavaServer Pages (JSP's). JSTL tags are used to include JSF UI
			components into the
			JSP. This is standard in JSF 1.2. The JSF 2.0
			version is
			using
			Facelets. 


