<section id="dojoserver">
	<title>Accessing the server</title>
	<section id="dojoserver_s2a">
		<title>Reading a fixed file from a server</title>
		<para>
			Dojo allows you to read data from the server. The following
			HTML page will connect the server and asynchronously load
			the content from the web server. In this example the loaded
			content is a static text page.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			<programlisting>
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
					parse="text" href="../examples/server/readServer.html" />
			</programlisting>
		</para>
		<para>
			<tip>
				This example may not be running on a local file system.
				If you do not see something try to replace the URL
				http://www.vogella.com/tutorials/AjaxwithDojo/download/includeTextFile.txt
				with a path to a local file. This should then also work
				with a local running HTML page.
			</tip>
		</para>
		<para>
			Start the HTML. The Dojo javascript will access the text
			file in the background and update the webpage with the
			information once the text file is read.
		</para>
		<para>
			Welcome to the world of Ajax! You successfully loaded a
			content from a website and included the response into your
			existing HTML page.

		</para>
	</section>

	<section id="dojoserver_s2b">
		<title>Send data to the server and update the page with the response</title>
		<para>
			Now you need a build a server side application. I'm going to
			use Java Servlets for this but you can use any other
			language on the server you like, e.g. Perl, PHP, etc.
		</para>
		<para>
			Create the following Java servlet, compile it and deploy it
			to your server. I'm going to assume that the servlet will be
			running on the URL yourhomepage/servlets/ReturnParameters.
		</para>
		<para>
			<programlisting>
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
					parse="text" href="../examples/server/ReturnParameters.java" />
			</programlisting>
		</para>
		<para>
			Now create the following HTML page which calls the servlet
			with two parameters and displays the result at a certain
			place in the application.
		</para>

		<para>
			<programlisting>
				<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
					parse="text" href="../examples/server/paratoServlet.html" />
			</programlisting>
		</para>

	</section>
</section>
