[[xml_overview">
== XML Introduction
[[xml_overview_s2a">
=== XML Overview
		
			XML is the abbreviation for
			_Extensible Markup Language_
			and is an established data exchange format. XML
			was defined
			1998 by
			the
			World Wide Web Consortium (W3C).
		
		
			An XML document consists of elements, each element has a
			start
			tag, content and an end tag. An XML document must have
			exactly
			one root
			element (i.e., one tag which encloses the
			remaining tags). XML
			differentiates between capital and non-capital letters.

		
		An XML file must be "well-formed".
		
			A
			_well-formed_
			XML file must apply to the following conditions:
			<itemizedlist>
				*
					An XML document always starts with a prolog (see
						below for an
						explanation of what a prolog is)
					
				
				*
					Every opening tag has a closing tag.
				
				*
					All tags are completely nested.
				
			
		

		
			An XML file is called
			_valid_
			if it is well-formed and if it is
			contains a link to an XML schema
			and
			is valid according to the schema.
		

[[xml_comparisionwithotherformats">
=== Comparison of XML to other formats

		
			XML has the following characteristics which makes processing it via
			computer programs relatively easy compared to a binary or
			unstructured
			format:
			<itemizedlist>
				*
					XML is plain text
				
				*
					XML represents data without defining how the data should be
						displayed
					
				
				*
					XML can be transformed into other formats via XSL
				
				*
					XML can be easily processed via standard parsers
					
				
				*
					XML files are hierarchical
				
			
		
		On the other side is XML format is relatively verbose, e.g., if
			data is
			represented as XML the size of this data is relatively large
			compared to other formats. In the Internet JSON or binary formats are
			frequently used to
			replace XML if the data throughput is important.
		


[[xml_overview_s2b">
=== XML Example
		The following is a valid, well-formed XML file.
		
[source,xml]
----
include::res/xmlintro/firstxmlfile.txt[]
----
		


[[xml_overview_s2c">
=== XML Elements
		
			An XML document always starts with a
			<code>prolog</code>
			which
			describes the XML file.
			This
			<code>prolog</code>
			can be minimal, e.g.
				<![CDATA[ <?xml version="1.0"?> ]]>
			or can contain other information, e.g. the encoding,
			e.g.
				<![CDATA[ <?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes" ?> ]]>
		
		
			A tag which does not enclose any content is know as an
			"empty tag".
			For
			example:

				<![CDATA[ <flag/> ]]>
		


	
		Comments in XML are defined as:
				<![CDATA[ <! COMMENT> ]]>
	



