<section id="javastax">
== Streaming API for XML (StaX)
	<section id="javastax_overview">
=== Overview
		
			Streaming API for XML, called StaX, is an API for
			reading
			and
			writing XML Documents.
		
		
			StaX is a Pull-Parsing model. Application can take the
			control
			over parsing the XML documents by pulling (taking)
			the events from the
			parser.
		
		
			The core StaX API falls into two categories and they are
			listed below.
			They are

			<itemizedlist>
				*
					Cursor API
				
				*
					Event Iterator API
				
			
		
		
			Applications can use any of these two API for parsing XML
			documents.
			The following will focus on the event iterator
			API as I consider it
			more convenient to use.
		


	<section id="javastax_api">
=== Event Iterator API
		
			The event iterator API has two main interfaces:
			XMLEventReader
			for parsing XML and XMLEventWriter for
			generating XML.
		



	<section id="javastax_read">
=== XMLEventReader - Read XML Example
		 This example is stored in project "de.vogella.xml.stax.reader".
		
		
			Applications loop over the entire document requesting for
			the
			Next Event. The Event Iterator API is implemented on top
			of the Cursor
			API.
		

		
			In this example we will read the following XML document and
			create objects from it.
		
		
[source,xml]
----
include::res/staxread/config.xml[]
----
		
		 Define therefore the following class to store the individual
			entries of the XML file.
		
		
[source,java]
----
include::res/staxread/Item.java[]
----
		
		
			The following reads the XML file and creates a List of object
			Items from the entries in the XML file.
		

		
[source,java]
----
include::res/staxread/StaXParser.java[]
----
		
		 You can test the parser via the following test program. Please
			note that the file `config.xml` must exist in the Java project folder.
		
		
[source,java]
----
include::res/staxread/TestRead.java[]
----
		


	<section id="javastax_write">
=== Write XML File Example
		 This example is stored in project "de.vogella.xml.stax.writer".
		
		
			Let's assume you would like to write the following simple XML
			file.
		
		
[source,xml]
----
include::res/staxwrite/config.xml[]
----
		
		
			StaX does not provide functionality to automatically format the XML file so you have to add end-of-lines and tab
			information to
			your XML file.
		

		
[source,java]
----
include::res/staxwrite/StaxWriter.java[]
----
		
		 And a little test.
		
[source,java]
----
include::res/staxwrite/TestWrite.java[]
----
		

		
			For another (more complex) example of using Stax, please see
http://www.vogella.com/tutorials/RSSFeed/article.html"> Reading and creating RSS feeds via Java (with Stax)</ulink>.
		


