<section id="javawebterminology_overview">
	<title>Web development</title>
	<section id="javawebterminology_overview1">
		<title>Webdevelopment with Java</title>
		<para>
			Java has strong support for web development. While Java on the
			desktop, with the notable exception of Eclipse RCP based application
			was never a huge success, Java is frequently used at the server side.
		</para>

	</section>
	<section id="overview_webdevelopment">
		<title>Web development</title>
		<para>If you develop a web application (independent of the
			programming
			language your are using), you typically put your web application on
			a
			dedicated server
			(and not your local computer). The web application
			runs on the
			server
			and people can access it there. The server is either
			a real machine
			(with CPU, memory, harddisk, etc.) or a virtual server
			which is
			basically a machine which is separated by software into
			smaller
			machines.
		</para>
		<para>
			It is possible to use your local computer as a server,
			but
			usually you want to have a fixed server which runs 24 hours per
			day,
			7
			days per week so that web clients can always reach your server
			under a
			pre-defined address.
		</para>
		<para>
			For example,
			<ulink url="http://blog.vogella.com/">blog.vogella.com</ulink>
			contains the vogella blog. This blog is a web application powered by
			WordPress
			which is a web application written in the server-side
			scripting language
			PHP.
		</para>
	</section>
	<section id="overview_servervscloud">
		<title>Server vs cloud deployment</title>
		<para>
			Instead of running your application directly on a dedicated
			server,
			you
			could also run it in a cloud environment. This cloud
			environment
			provides the necessary server for your application. An
			example for
			this is the Google App Engine which allows to host web
			applications written in different programming languages.
		</para>

	</section>
	<section id="overview_container">
		<title>Java web or Java EE container</title>
		<para> Java web applications are typically not running directly on the
			server. Java web applications are running inside a web container on
			the
			server.
		</para>
		<para>
			The container provides a
			runtime environment for Java web
			applications.
			The container is for
			Java web applications what the JVM
			(Java Virtual
			Machine) is for local
			running Java applications. The
			container itself
			runs in the JVM.
		</para>
		<para>In general, Java distinguishes two containers: the web container
			and the Java EE container. Typical web containers in the Java world
			are Tomcat or Jetty. A web container supports the execution of Java
			servlets and
			JavaServer Pages. A Java EE container supports additional
			functionality, for example, distribution of server load.
		</para>
		<para>Most of the modern Java web frameworks are based on servlets.
			Popular Java web frameworks are GWT, JavaServer
			Faces,
			Struts and the
			Spring framework.
			These
			web frameworks usually require as a minimum
			container a web
			container.
		</para>
	</section>
	
</section>